<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--<?xml-model href="OdysseySchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<?xml-model href="out/HomerOdysseyODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="out/HomerOdysseyODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>HomerOdysseyFaglesTranslation</title>
            <author>Homer</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Claire Zak</name>
               <resp>conversion to TEI-conformant document</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>HIST630 Digital Methods for Historical Research course</publisher>
            <date when="2023-02-21">21 February 2023</date>
            <idno type="filename">HomerOdysseyFaglesTranslation.xml</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>This text is freely available provided the text is distributed with the header information provided</p>
               <p xml:lang="en">The text has been translated from Greek to English</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
           <bibl>
              <author>Robert Fagles</author>
              <title>The Odyssey</title>
              <publisher>Penguin Classics</publisher>
              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
              <date when="1990"></date>
           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
           <p>TEI-compliant document created for the HIST630 course at Texas A&amp;M University</p>
        </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <creation>
           <date when="2023-02-14">14 February 2023</date>
        </creation>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <listChange>
           <change when="2023-02-14">imported document</change>
           <change when="2023-02-21">created header and document structure</change>
        </listChange>
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <front>
        <docAuthor rend="allCaps"> <persName type= "author">HOMER</persName> </docAuthor>
           <docTitle rend="allCaps"> <titlePart type="main">THE ODYSSEY</titlePart> </docTitle>
        <byline rend="allCaps"> TRANSLATED BY <persName type= "translator">Robert Fagles</persName> </byline>
     </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Book I <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName> Inspires the <rs ref="#pers002">Prince</rs></head>
<l>Sing to me of the <rs ref="#pers003">man</rs>, <persName type="deity" ref="#pers004">Muse</persName>, the <rs ref="#pers003">man</rs> of twists and turns ...</l> 
<l>driven time and again off course, once <rs ref="#pers003">he</rs> had plundered</l> 
<l>the hallowed heights of <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l>Many cities of men <rs ref="#pers003">he</rs> saw and learned their minds,</l>
<l>many pains <rs ref="#pers003">he</rs> suffered, heartsick on the open sea,</l>
<l>fighting to save <rs ref="#pers003">his</rs> life and bring <rs ref="#pers003">his</rs> comrades home.</l>
<l>But <rs ref="#pers003">he</rs> could not save them from disaster, hard as <rs ref="#pers003">he</rs> strove—</l> 
<l>the recklessness of their own ways destroyed them all,</l>
<l>the blind fools, they devoured the cattle of the <rs type="deity" ref="#pers005">Sun</rs></l>
<l>and the <rs type="deity" ref="#pers005">Sungod</rs> blotted out the day of their return.</l>
<l>Launch out on <rs ref="#pers003">his</rs> story, <persName type="deity" ref="#pers004">Muse</persName>, daughter of <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName>,</l>
<l>start from where <rs ref="#pers004">you</rs> will—sing for our time too.</l>
<l>By now, all the survivors, all who avoided headlong death</l>
<l>were safe at home, escaped the wars and waves.</l>    
<l>But one <rs ref="#pers003">man</rs> alone ...</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers003">his</rs> heart set on <rs ref="#pers003">his</rs> <rs ref="#pers007">wife</rs> and <rs ref="#pers003">his</rs> return— <persName type="deity" ref="#pers008">Calypso</persName>,</l>
<l>the bewitching nymph, the lustrous goddess, held him back,</l> 
<l>deep in her arching caverns, craving him for a husband.</l>
<l>But then, when the wheeling seasons brought the year around,</l> 
<l>that year spun out by the gods when he should reach his home,</l>
<l><placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>—though not even there would he be free of trials,</l>
<l>even among his loved ones—then every god took pity,</l>
<l>all except <persName type="deity" ref="#pers009">Poseidon</persName>. He raged on, seething against</l>
<l>the great <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> till he reached his <rs ref="#place002">native land</rs>.</l>
<l>But now Poseidon had gone to visit the <orgName ref="#org003">Ethiopians</orgName> worlds away,</l>
<l><orgName ref="#org003">Ethiopians</orgName> off at the farthest limits of mankind,</l>
<l>a people split in two, one part where the <rs ref="#pers005">Sungod</rs> sets</l>
<l>and part where the <rs ref="#pers005">Sungod</rs> rises. There <persName type="deity" ref="#pers009">Poseidon</persName> went</l>
<l>to receive an offering, bulls and rams by the hundred—</l> 
<l>far away at the feast the <rs ref="#pers009">Sea-lord</rs> sat and took his pleasure.</l>
<l>But the other gods, at home in <rs>Olympian<persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus’s</persName></rs> halls,</l>
<l>met for full assembly there, and among them now</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers006">the father of men and gods</rs> was first to speak,</l>
<l>sorely troubled, remembering handsome <persName ref="#pers011">Aegisthus</persName>,</l>
<l>the man <rs ref="#pers013"><persName ref="#pers012">Agamemnon</persName>’s son</rs>, renowned <persName ref="#pers013">Orestes</persName>, killed.</l>
<l>Recalling <persName ref="#pers011">Aegisthus</persName>, <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName> harangued the immortal powers:</l>
<l>“Ah how shameless—the way these mortals blame the gods.</l>
<l>From us alone, they say, come all their miseries, yes,</l>
<l>but they themselves, with their own reckless ways,</l>
<l>compound their pains beyond their proper share.</l>
<l>Look at <persName ref="#pers011">Aegisthus</persName> now ...</l>
<l>above and beyond his share he stole <rs ref="#pers014"><rs ref="#pers012">Atrides</rs>’ wife</rs>,</l>
<l>he murdered <rs ref="#pers012">the warlord</rs> coming home from <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName></l><l>though he knew it meant his own total ruin.</l>
<l>Far in advance we told <rs ref="#pers011">him</rs> so ourselves,</l>
<l>dispatching the guide, the <rs ref="#pers015">giant-killer</rs> <persName type="deity" ref="#pers015">Hermes</persName>.</l>
<l>‘Don’t murder <rs ref="#pers012">the man</rs>,’ <rs ref="#pers015">he</rs> said, ‘don’t court <rs ref="#pers014">his wife</rs>.</l>
<l>Beware, revenge will come from <persName ref="#pers013">Orestes</persName>, <rs ref="#pers013"><persName ref="#pers012">Agamemnon</persName>’s son</rs>,</l>
<l>that day he comes of age and longs for <rs ref="#place003">his native land</rs>.’</l>
<l>So <persName type="deity" ref="#pers015">Hermes</persName> warned, with all the good will in the world,</l>
<l>but would <persName ref="#pers011">Aegisthus</persName>’ hardened heart give way? </l>
<l>Now he pays the price—all at a single stroke.”</l>
<l>And <rs ref="#pers001">sparkling-eyed</rs> <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName> drove the matter home:</l>
<l>“<rs ref="#pers006">Father</rs>, son of <persName type="deity" ref="#pers016">Cronus</persName>, our high and mighty king,</l>
<l>surely <rs ref="#pers011">he</rs> goes down to a death he earned in full!</l>
<l>Let them all die so, all who do such things.</l>
<l>But my heart breaks for <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>,</l>
<l>that <rs ref="#pers003">seasoned veteran cursed by fate</rs> so long—</l>
<l>far from his loved ones still, he suffers torments</l>
<l>off on a <rs ref="#place004">wave-washed island</rs> rising at the center of the seas.</l>
<l>A dark wooded island, and there a <rs ref="#pers008">goddess</rs> makes her home,</l>
<l>daughter of <persName type="deity" ref="#pers017">Atlas</persName>, <rs ref="#pers017">wicked Titan who sounds the deep</rs></l>
<l>in all its depths, <rs ref="#pers017">whose shoulders lift on high</rs></l>
<l><rs ref="#pers017">the colossal pillars thrusting earth and sky apart</rs>.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers008"><persName type="deity" ref="#pers017">Atlas</persName>’ daughter</rs> it is who holds <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> captive,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers003">luckless man</rs>—despite his tears, forever trying</l>
<l>to spellbind his heart with suave, seductive words</l>
<l>and wipe all thought of <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName> from his mind.</l>
<l>But he, straining for no more than a glimpse</l>
<l>of hearth-smoke drifting up from his own land,</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> longs to die ...</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers006">Olympian <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName></rs>, have you no care for him in your lofty heart?</l>
<l>Did he never win your favor with sacrifices</l>
<l>burned beside the ships on the broad plain of <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName>?</l>
<l>Why, <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName>, why so dead set against <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>?”</l>
<l>“<rs ref="#pers001">My child</rs>,” <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName> <rs ref="#pers006">who marshals the thunderheads</rs> replied,</l>
<l>“what nonsense you let slip through your teeth. Now,</l>
<l>how on earth could I forget <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>? Great <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName></l>
<l>who excels all men in wisdom, excels in offerings too</l>
<l>he gives the immortal gods who rule the vaulting skies?</l>
<l>No, it’s the <rs ref="#pers009">Earth-Shaker</rs>, <persName type="deity" ref="#pers009">Poseidon</persName>, unappeased,</l>
<l>forever fuming against him for the <rs ref="#pers018">Cyclops</rs></l>
<l>whose giant eye he blinded: <rs ref="#pers018">godlike <persName type="deity" ref="#pers018">Polyphemus</persName></rs>,</l>
<l>towering over all the <orgName ref="#org004">Cyclops</orgName>’ clans in power.</l>
<l>The nymph <persName type="deity" ref="#pers019">Thoosa</persName> bore him, daughter of <persName type="deity" ref="#pers020">Phorcys</persName>,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers020">lord of the barren salt sea</rs>—<rs ref="#pers019">she</rs> met <persName type="deity" ref="#pers009">Poseidon</persName></l>
<l>once in his vaulted caves and they made love.</l>
<l>And now for <rs ref="#pers009">his <rs ref="#pers018">blinded son</rs> the earthquake god</rs>—</l>
<l>though <rs ref="#pers009">he</rs> won’t quite kill <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>—</l>
<l>drives him far off course from <rs ref="#place002">native land</rs>.</l>
<l>But come, all of us here put heads together now,</l>
<l>work out his journey home so <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> can return.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers009">Lord <persName type="deity" ref="#pers009">Poseidon</persName></rs>, I trust, will let his anger go.</l>
<l>How can he stand his ground against the will</l>
<l>of all the gods at once—one god alone?”</l>
<l><persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName>, her eyes flashing bright, exulted,</l>
<l>“<rs ref="#pers006">Father</rs>, <rs ref="#pers006">son of <persName type="deity" ref="#pers016">Cronus</persName></rs>, our high and mighty king!</l>
<l>If now it really pleases the blissful gods</l>
<l>that <rs ref="#pers003">wise <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName></rs> shall return—home at last—</l>
<l>let us dispatch the guide and <rs ref="#pers015">giant-killer</rs> <persName type="deity" ref="#pers015">Hermes</persName></l>
<l>down to <placeName ref="#place004">Ogygia Island</placeName>, down to announce at once</l>
<l>to <rs ref="#pers008">the nymph with lovely braids</rs> our fixed decree:</l> 
<l><persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> journeys home—the exile must return!</l>
<l>While I myself go down to <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>, rouse his <rs ref="#pers002">son</rs></l>
<l>to a braver pitch, inspire his heart with courage</l>
<l>to summon the <rs>flowing-haired <orgName ref="#org005">Achaeans</orgName></rs> to full assembly,</l>
<l>speak his mind to all those <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName>, slaughtering on and on</l>
<l>his droves of sheep and shambling longhorn cattle.</l>
<l>Next I will send him off to <placeName ref="#place005">Sparta</placeName> and sandy <placeName ref="#place006">Pylos</placeName>,</l>
<l>there to learn of his <rs ref="#pers003">dear father’s</rs> journey home.</l>
<l>Perhaps he will hear some news and make his name</l>
<l>throughout the mortal world.”</l>
<l>So <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName> vowed and under her feet she fastened the supple sandals,</l>
<l>ever-glowing gold, that wing her over the waves</l>
<l>and boundless earth with the rush of gusting winds.</l>
<l>She seized the rugged spear tipped with a bronze point—</l>
<l>weighted, heavy, the massive shaft she wields to break the lines</l>
<l>of heroes <rs ref="#pers001">the mighty Father’s daughter</rs> storms against.</l>
<l>And down she swept from <placeName ref="#place007">Olympus</placeName>’ craggy peaks</l>
<l>and lit on <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>, standing tall at <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>’ gates,</l>
<l>the threshold of his court. Gripping her bronze spear,</l>
<l>she looked for all the world like a stranger now,</l>
<l>like <persName ref="#pers021">Mentes</persName>, <rs ref="#pers021">lord of the <orgName ref="#org001">Taphians</orgName></rs>.</l>
<l>There she found the swaggering <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName>, just then </l>
<l>amusing themselves with rolling dice before the doors,</l>
<l>lounging on hides of oxen they had killed themselves. </l>
<l>While <orgName ref="#org006">heralds</orgName> and brisk <orgName ref="#org007">attendants</orgName> bustled round them,</l>
<l>some at the mixing-bowls, mulling wine and water,</l>
<l>others wiping the tables down with sopping sponges,</l>
<l>setting them out in place, still other servants</l>
<l>jointed and carved the great sides of meat.</l>
<l>First by far to see her was <rs ref="#pers002">Prince <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName></rs>,</l>
<l>sitting among the <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName>, heart obsessed with grief.</l>
<l>He could almost see his magnificent <rs ref="#pers003">father</rs>, here ...</l>
<l>in the mind’s eye—if only he might drop from the clouds</l>
<l>and drive these <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName> all in a rout throughout the halls</l>
<l>and regain his pride of place and rule his own domains!</l>
<l>Daydreaming so as he sat among the <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName>,</l>
<l>he glimpsed <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName> now</l>
<l>and straight to the porch he went, mortified</l>
<l>that a guest might still be standing at the doors.</l>
<l>Pausing beside her there, he clasped her right hand</l>
<l>and relieving her at once of her long bronze spear,</l>
<l>met her with winged words: “Greetings, <rs ref="#pers001">stranger</rs>!</l>
<l>Here in our house you’ll find a royal welcome.</l>
<l>Have supper first, then tell us what you need.”</l>
<l>He led the way and <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Pallas Athena</persName> followed.</l>
<l>Once in the high-roofed hall, he took her lance</l>
<l>and fixed it firm in a burnished rack against</l>
<l>a sturdy pillar, there where row on row of spears,</l> 
<l>embattled <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>’ spears, stood stacked and waiting.</l>
<l>Then <rs ref="#pers002">he</rs> escorted her to a high, elaborate chair of honor,</l>
<l>over it draped a cloth, and here he placed <rs ref="#pers001">his guest</rs></l>
<l>with a stool to rest her feet. But for himself</l>
<l>he drew up a low reclining chair beside her,</l>
<l>richly painted, clear of the press of <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName>,</l>
<l>concerned his guest, offended by their uproar,</l>
<l>might shrink from food in the midst of such a mob.</l>
<l>He hoped, what’s more, to ask him about <rs ref="#pers003">his long-lost father</rs>.</l>
<l>A maid brought water soon in a graceful golden pitcher</l>
<l>and over a silver basin tipped it out</l>
<l>so they might rinse their hands,</l>
<l>then pulled a gleaming table to their side.</l>
<l>A staid housekeeper brought on bread to serve them,</l>
<l>appetizers aplenty too, lavish with her bounty.</l>
<l>A carver lifted platters of meat toward them,</l>
<l>meats of every sort, and set beside them golden cups</l>
<l>and time and again a page came round and poured them wine.</l>
<l>But now the <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName> trooped in with all their swagger</l>
<l>and took their seats on low and high-backed chairs.</l>
<l><orgName ref="#org006">Heralds</orgName> poured water over their hands for rinsing,</l>
<l><orgName ref="#org008">serving maids</orgName> brought bread heaped high in trays</l>
<l>and <orgName ref="#org007">the young men</orgName> brimmed the mixing-bowls with wine.</l>
<l>They reached out for the good things that lay at hand,</l>
<l>and when they’d put aside desire for food and drink</l>
<l>the <orgName ref="#org002">suitors</orgName> set their minds on other pleasures,</l>
<l>song and dancing, all that crowns a feast.</l>
<l>A herald placed an ornate lyre in <persName ref="#pers022">Phemius</persName>’ hands,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers022">the bard</rs> who always performed among them there;</l>
<l><rs>they</rs> forced the man to sing.</l>
<l>A rippling prelude— and no sooner had he struck up his rousing song</l>
<l>than <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName>, head close to <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName>’s sparkling eyes,</l>
<l>spoke low to his guest so no one else could hear:</l>
<l>“Dear <rs ref="#pers001">stranger</rs>, would you be shocked by what I say?</l>
<l>Look at <rs>them</rs> over there. Not a care in the world,</l>
<l>just lyres and tunes! Easy for them, all right,</l>
<l>they feed on another’s goods and go scot-free—</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers003">a man whose white bones lie strewn in the rain somewhere</rs>,</l>
<l>rotting away on land or rolling down the ocean’s salty swells.</l>
<l>But that man—if they caught sight of him home in <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>,</l>
<l>by god, they’d all pray to be faster on their feet</l>
<l>than richer in bars of gold and heavy robes.</l>
<l>But now, no use, <rs ref="#pers003">he’s</rs> died a wretched death.</l>
<l>No comfort’s left for us ... not even if</l>
<l>someone, somewhere, says he’s coming home.</l>
<l>The day of his return will never dawn.</l>
<l>Enough. Tell me about yourself now, clearly, point by point.</l>
<l>Who are you? where are you from? your city? your parents?</l>
<l>What sort of vessel brought you? Why did the sailors</l>
<l>land you here in <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>? Who did they say they are?</l>
<l>I hardly think you came this way on foot!</l>
<l>And tell me this for a fact—I need to know—</l>
<l>is this your first time here? Or are you a friend of <rs ref="#pers003">father’s</rs>,</l>
<l>a guest from the old days? Once, crowds of other men </l>
<l>would come to our house on visits—visitor that he was, </l>
<l>when he walked among the living.”</l>
<l>Her eyes glinting, <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">goddess Athena</persName> answered, “My whole story, of course,</l>
<l>I’ll tell it point by point. Wise old <persName ref="#pers023">Anchialus</persName></l>
<l>was my father. My own name is <persName ref="#pers021">Mentes</persName>,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers021">lord of the <orgName ref="#org001">Taphian</orgName> men who love their oars</rs>.</l>
<l>And here <rs ref="#pers001">I’ve</rs> come, just now, with ship and crew,</l>
<l>sailing the wine-dark sea to foreign ports of call,</l>
<l>to <placeName ref="#place008">Temese</placeName>, out for bronze—our cargo gleaming iron.</l>
<l>Our ship lies moored off farmlands far from town,</l>
<l>riding in <placeName ref="#place009">Rithron Cove</placeName>, beneath <placeName ref="#place010">Mount Nion</placeName>’s woods.</l>
<l>As for the ties between <rs ref="#pers003">your father</rs> and <rs ref="#pers001">myself</rs>,</l>
<l>we’ve been friends forever, I’m proud to say,</l>
<l>and he would bear me out</l>
<l>if you went and questioned <rs ref="#pers024">old lord</rs> <persName ref="#pers024">Laertes</persName>.</l>
<l>He, I gather, no longer ventures into town</l>
<l>but lives a life of hardship, all to himself,</l>
<l>off on his farmstead with an aged serving-woman</l>
<l>who tends him well, who gives him food and drink</l>
<l>when weariness has taken hold of his withered limbs</l> 
<l>from hauling himself along his vineyard’s steep slopes.</l>
<l>And now I’ve come—and why? I heard that <rs ref="#pers003">he</rs> was back ...</l>
<l>your father, that is. But no, the gods thwart his passage.</l>
<l>Yet I tell you great <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> is not dead. He’s still alive,</l>
<l>somewhere in this wide world, held captive, out at sea </l>
<l>on a wave-washed island, and hard men, savages,</l>
<l>somehow hold him back against his will.</l>
<l>Wait, I’ll make you a prophecy, one the immortal gods</l>
<l>have planted in my mind—it will come true, I think,</l>
<l>though I’m hardly a seer or know the flights of birds.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers003">He</rs> won’t be gone long from <rs ref="#place002">the native land he loves</rs>,</l>
<l>not even if iron shackles bind your father down.</l>
<l>He’s plotting a way to journey home at last;</l>
<l>he’s never at a loss.</l>
<l>But come, please, tell me about yourself now, point by point.</l>
<l>You’re truly <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>’ son? You’ve sprung up so!</l>
<l>Uncanny resemblance ... the head, and the fine eyes—</l>
<l>I see him now. How often we used to meet in the old days</l>
<l>before he embarked for <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName>, where <orgName ref="#org009">other Argive captains</orgName>,</l>
<l>all the best men, sailed in the long curved ships.</l>
<l>From then to this very day</l>
<l>I’ve not set eyes on <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> or he on me.”</l>
<l>And young <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName> cautiously replied,</l>
<l>“I’ll try, my friend, to give you a frank answer.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers007">Mother</rs> has always told me I’m his son, it’s true,</l>
<l>but I am not so certain. Who, on his own,</l>
<l>has ever really known who gave him life?</l>
<l>Would to god I’d been the son of a happy man</l>
<l>whom old age overtook in the midst of his possessions!</l>
<l>Now, think of the most unlucky mortal ever born—</l>
<l>since you ask me, yes, they say I am his son.”</l>
<l>“Still,” <rs ref="#pers001">the clear-eyed goddess</rs> reassured him,</l>
<l>“trust me, the gods have not marked out your house</l>
<l>for such an unsung future,</l>
<l>not if <persName ref="#pers007">Penelope</persName> has borne a son like you.</l>
<l>But tell me about all this and spare me nothing.</l>
<l>What’s this banqueting, this crowd carousing here?</l>
<l>And what part do you play yourself? Some wedding-feast,</l>
<l>some festival? Hardly a potluck supper, I would say.</l>
<l>How obscenely they lounge and swagger here, look,</l>
<l>gorging in your house. Why, any man of sense</l>
<l>who chanced among them would be outraged,</l>
<l>seeing such behavior.”</l>
<l>Ready <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName> took her up at once: “Well, <rs ref="#pers001">my friend</rs>,</l>
<l>seeing you want to probe and press the question,</l>
<l>once this house was rich, no doubt, beyond reproach</l>
<l>when <rs ref="#pers001">the man you mentioned</rs> still lived here, at home.</l>
<l>Now the gods have reversed our fortunes with a vengeance—</l>
<l>wiped that man from the earth like no one else before.</l>
<l>I would never have grieved so much about his death</l>
<l>if he’d gone down with comrades off in <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName></l>
<l>or died in the arms of loved ones,</l>
<l>once he had wound down the long coil of war.</l>
<l>Then all united <placeName ref="#place018">Achaea</placeName> would have raised his tomb</l>
<l>and he’d have won his son great fame for years to come.</l>
<l>But now the whirlwinds have ripped him away, no fame for him!</l>
<l>He’s lost and gone now—out of sight, out of mind—and I ...</l>
<l>he’s left me tears and grief. Nor do I rack my heart</l>
<l>and grieve for him alone. No longer. Now the gods</l>
<l>have invented other miseries to plague me.</l>
<l>Listen. <rs>All the nobles who rule the islands round about</rs>,</l>
<l><placeName ref="#place011">Dulichion</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#place012">Same</placeName>, and wooded <placeName ref="#place013">Zacynthus</placeName> too,</l>
<l>and all who lord it in rocky <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName> as well—</l>
<l>down to the last man they court <rs ref="#pers007">my mother</rs>,</l>
<l>they lay waste my house! And <rs ref="#pers007">mother</rs> ...</l>
<l>she neither rejects a marriage she despises</l>
<l>nor can she bear to bring the courting to an end—</l>
<l>while they continue to bleed my household white.</l>
<l>Soon—you wait—they’ll grind me down as well.”</l>
<l>“Shameful!”— brimming with indignation, <persName ref="#pers001">Pallas Athena</persName> broke out.</l>
<l>“Oh how much you need <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>, gone so long—</l>
<l>how he’d lay hands on all <orgName ref="#org002">these brazen suitors</orgName>!</l>
<l>If only he would appear, now,</l>
<l>at his house’s outer gates and take his stand,</l>
<l>armed with his helmet, shield and pair of spears,</l>
<l>as strong as the man I glimpsed that first time</l>
<l>in our own house, drinking wine and reveling there ...</l>
<l>just come in from <placeName ref="#place014">Ephyra</placeName>, visiting <persName ref="#pers025">Ilus</persName>, <persName ref="#pers026">Mermerus</persName>’ son.</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> sailed that way, you see, in his swift trim ship,</l>
<l>hunting deadly poison to smear on his arrows’ bronze heads.</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers025">Ilus</persName> refused—he feared the wrath of the everlasting gods—</l>
<l>but <rs ref="#pers003">father</rs>, so fond of <rs ref="#pers025">him</rs>, gave <rs ref="#pers025">him</rs> all he wanted.</l>
<l>If only that <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> sported with <orgName ref="#org002">these suitors</orgName>,</l>
<l>a blood wedding, a quick death would take the lot!</l>
<l>True, but all lies in the lap of the great gods,</l>
<l>whether or not he’ll come and pay them back,</l>
<l>here, in his own house.</l>
<l>But <rs ref="#pers002">you</rs>, I urge you, think how to drive <orgName ref="#org002">these suitors</orgName> from your halls.</l>
<l>Come now, listen closely. Take my words to heart.</l>
<l>At daybreak summon the island’s lords to full assembly,</l>
<l>give your orders to all and call the gods to witness:</l>
<l>tell <orgName ref="#org002">the suitors</orgName> to scatter, each to his own place.</l>
<l>As for <rs ref="#pers007">your mother</rs>, if the spirit moves her to marry,</l>
<l>let her go back to <rs ref="#pers027">her father</rs>’s house, <rs ref="#pers027">a man of power</rs>.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers007">Her</rs> kin will arrange the wedding, provide the gifts,</l>
<l>the array that goes with a daughter dearly loved.</l>
<l>For <rs ref="#pers002">you</rs>, I have some good advice, if only you will accept it.</l>
<l>Fit out a ship with twenty oars, the best in sight,</l>
<l>sail in quest of news of <rs ref="#pers003">your long-lost father</rs>.</l>
<l>Someone may tell you something</l>
<l>or you may catch a rumor straight from <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName>,</l>
<l>rumor that carries news to men like nothing else.</l>
<l>First go down to <placeName ref="#place006">Pylos</placeName>, question <persName ref="#pers028">old King Nestor</persName>,</l>
<l>then cross over to <placeName ref="#place005">Sparta</placeName>, to <persName ref="#pers029">red-haired Menelaus</persName>,</l>
<l>of all <orgName ref="#org005">the bronze-armored Achaeans</orgName> the last man back.</l>
<l>Now, if you hear <rs ref="#pers003">your father</rs>’s alive and heading home,</l>
<l>hard-pressed as you are, brave out one more year.</l>
<l>If you hear he’s dead, no longer among the living,</l>
<l>then back you come to <rs ref="#place002">the native land</rs> you love.</l>
<l>raise his grave-mound, build his honors high</l>
<l>with the full funeral rites that he deserves—</l>
<l>and give <rs ref="#pers007">your mother</rs> to another husband.</l>
<l>Then, once you’ve sealed those matters, seen them through,</l>
<l>think hard, reach down deep in your heart and soul</l>
<l>for a way to kill <orgName ref="#org002">these suitors</orgName> in your house,</l>
<l>by stealth or in open combat.</l>
<l>You must not cling to your boyhood any longer—</l>
<l>it’s time you were a man. Haven’t you heard</l>
<l>what glory <persName ref="#pers013">Prince Orestes</persName> won throughout the world</l>
<l>when he killed that <persName ref="#pers011">cunning, murderous Aegisthus</persName>,</l>
<l>who’d killed <rs ref="#pers012">his famous father</rs>?</l>
<l>And you, my friend— how tall and handsome I see you now—be brave, you too,</l>
<l>so men to come will sing your praises down the years.</l>
<l>But now I must go back to my swift trim ship</l>
<l>and all my shipmates, chafing there, I’m sure,</l>
<l>waiting for my return. It all rests with you.</l>
<l>Take my words to heart.”</l>
<l>“<rs ref="#pers001">Oh stranger</rs>,” <persName ref="#pers002">heedful Telemachus</persName> replied, “indeed I will.</l>
<l>You’ve counseled me with so much kindness now,</l>
<l>like a father to a son. I won’t forget a word.</l>
<l>But come, stay longer, keen as you are to sail,</l>
<l>so you can bathe and rest and lift your spirits,</l>
<l>then go back to your ship, delighted with a gift,</l>
<l>a prize of honor, something rare and fine</l>
<l>as a keepsake from myself. The kind of gift</l>
<l>a host will give a stranger, friend to friend.”</l>
<l>Her eyes glinting, <persName ref="#pers001">Pallas</persName> declined in haste:</l>
<l>“Not now. Don’t hold me here. I long to be on my way.</l>
<l>As for the gift—whatever you’d give in kindness—</l>
<l>save it for my return so I can take it home.</l>
<l>Choose something rare and fine, and a good reward</l>
<l>that gift is going to bring you.”</l>
            <l>With that promise, off and away <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName><rs>the bright-eyed goddess</rs> flew</l>
<l>like a bird in soaring flight</l>
<l>but left <rs ref="#pers002">his</rs> spirit filled with nerve and courage,</l>
<l>charged with <rs ref="#pers003">his father</rs>’s memory more than ever now.</l>
<l>He felt his senses quicken, overwhelmed with wonder—</l>
<l>this was a <rs ref="#pers001">god</rs>, he knew it well and made at once</l>
<l>for <orgName ref="#org002">the suitors</orgName>, <rs ref="#pers002">a man like a god himself</rs>.</l>
<l>Amidst them still <rs ref="#pers022">the famous bard</rs> sang on, and <rs>they</rs> sat in silence, listening</l>
<l>as <rs ref="#pers022">he</rs> performed <orgName ref="#org005">The Achaeans</orgName>’ Journey Home from <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName>,</l>
<l>all the blows <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName> doomed <rs>them</rs> to endure.</l>
<l>And now, from high above in <rs ref="#pers007">her</rs> room and deep in thought,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers007">she</rs> caught <rs ref="#pers022">his</rs> inspired strains ...</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers007"><persName ref="#pers027">Icarius</persName>’ daughter Penelope</persName>, wary and reserved,</l>
<l>and down the steep stair from her chamber she descended,</l>
<l>not alone: two of her women followed close behind.</l>
<l>That radiant woman, once she reached <rs>her suitors</rs>,</l>
<l>drawing her glistening veil across her cheeks,</l>
<l>paused now where a column propped the sturdy roof,</l>
<l>with one of her loyal handmaids stationed either side.</l>
<l>Suddenly, dissolving in tears and bursting through</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers022">the bard</rs>’s inspired voice, <rs ref="#pers007">she</rs> cried out, “<persName ref="#pers022">Phemius</persName>!</l>
<l>So many other songs you know to hold us spellbound,</l>
<l>works of the gods and men that singers celebrate.</l>
<l>Sing one of those as you sit beside <rs>them</rs> here</l>
<l>and they drink their wine in silence.</l>
<l>But break off this song— the unendurable song that always rends the heart inside me ...</l>
<l>the unforgettable grief, it wounds me most of all!</l>
<l>How I long for <rs ref="#pers003">my husband</rs>—alive in memory, always, </l>
<l>that great man whose fame resounds through <placeName ref="#place015">Hellas</placeName></l>
<l>right to the depths of <placeName ref="#place016">Argos</placeName>!”</l>
<l>“Why, <rs ref="#pers007">mother</rs>,” poised <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName> put in sharply, “why deny</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers022">our devoted bard</rs> the chance to entertain us</l>
<l>any way the spirit stirs him on?</l>
<l>Bards are not to blame—</l>
<l><persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName> is to blame. He deals to each and every</l>
<l>laborer on this earth whatever doom he pleases.</l>
<l>Why fault the bard if he sings the <orgName ref="#org009">Argives</orgName>’ harsh fate?</l>
<l>It’s always the latest song, the one that echoes last</l>
<l>in the listeners’ ears, that people praise the most.</l>
<l>Courage, <rs ref="#pers007">mother</rs>. Harden your heart, and listen.</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> was scarcely the only one, you know,</l>
<l>whose journey home was blotted out at <placeName ref="#place001">Troy</placeName>.</l>
<l>Others, so many others, died there too.</l>
<l>So, <rs ref="#pers007">mother</rs>, go back to your quarters. Tend to your own tasks,</l>
<l>the distaff and the loom, and keep the women</l>
<l>working hard as well. As for giving orders,</l>
<l>men will see to that, but I most of all:</l>
<l>I hold the reins of power in this house.”</l>
<l>Astonished, <rs ref="#pers007">she</rs> withdrew to her own room. She took to heart</l>
<l>the clear good sense in what <rs ref="#pers002">her son</rs> had said.</l>
<l>Climbing up to the lofty chamber with her women,</l>
<l>she fell to weeping for <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName>, <rs ref="#pers003">her beloved husband</rs>,</l>
<l>till <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">watchful Athena</persName> sealed <rs ref="#pers007">her</rs> eyes with welcome sleep.</l>
<l>But <orgName ref="#org002">the suitors</orgName> broke into uproar through the shadowed</l>
<l>halls, all of them lifting prayers to lie beside <rs ref="#pers007">her</rs>, share her bed,</l>
<l>until <persName ref="#pers002">discreet Telemachus</persName> took command: “<orgName ref="#org002">You suitors</orgName></l>
<l>who plague <rs ref="#pers007">my mother</rs>, you, you insolent, overweening ...</l>
<l>for this evening let us dine and take our pleasure,</l>
<l>no more shouting now. What a fine thing it is</l>
<l>to listen to <rs ref="#pers022">such a bard as we have here</rs>—</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers022">the man sings like a god</rs>.</l>
<l>But at first light we all march forth to assembly, take our seats</l>
<l>so I can give my orders and say to you straight out:</l>
<l><rs>You</rs> must leave my palace! See to your feasting elsewhere,</l>
<l>devour your own possessions, house to house by turns.</l>
<l>But if you decide the fare is better, richer here,</l>
<l>destroying one man’s goods and going scot-free,</l>
<l>all right then, carve away!</l>
<l>But I’ll cry out to the everlasting gods in hopes</l>
<l>that <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName> will pay you back with a vengeance—all of you</l>
<l>destroyed in my house while I go scot-free myself!”</l>
<l>So <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName> declared. And they all bit their lips,</l>
<l>amazed <rs ref="#pers002">the prince</rs> could speak with so much daring.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers031"><persName ref="#pers030">Eupithes</persName>’ son</rs> <persName ref="#pers031">Antinous</persName> broke their silence:</l>
<l>“Well, <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName>, only the gods could teach you</l>
<l>to sound so high and mighty! Such brave talk.</l>
<l>I pray that <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName> will never make you king of <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>,</l>
<l>though <rs ref="#pers003">your father</rs>’s crown is no doubt <rs ref="#pers002">yours</rs> by birth.”</l>
<l>But <persName ref="#pers002">cool-headed Telemachus</persName> countered firmly:</l>
<l>“<persName ref="#pers031">Antinous</persName>, even though my words may offend you,</l>
<l>I’d be happy to take the crown if <persName type="deity" ref="#pers006">Zeus</persName> presents it.</l>
<l>You think that nothing worse could befall a man?</l>
<l>It’s really not so bad to be a king. All at once</l>
<l>your palace grows in wealth, your honors grow as well.</l>
<l>But there are hosts of other <orgName ref="#org005">Achaean princes,</orgName> look—</l>
<l>young and old, crowds of them on <placeName ref="#place002">our island here</placeName>—</l>
<l>and any one of the lot might hold the throne,</l>
<l>now great <persName ref="#pers003">Odysseus</persName> is dead ...</l>
<l>But I’ll be lord of my own house and servants,</l>
<l>all that <persName ref="#pers003">King Odysseus</persName> won for me by force.”</l>
<l>And now <persName ref="#pers032">Eurymachus</persName>, <rs><persName ref="#pers033">Polybus</persName>’ son</rs>, stepped in:</l>
<l>“Surely this must lie in the gods’ lap, <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName>—</l>
<l>which <orgName ref="#org005">Achaean</orgName> will lord it over <placeName ref="#place002">seagirt Ithaca</placeName>.</l>
<l>Do hold on to your own possessions, rule your house.</l>
<l>God forbid that anyone tear your holdings from your hands</l>
<l>while men still live in <placeName ref="#place002">Ithaca</placeName>.</l>
<l>But about <rs ref="#pers001">your guest</rs>, <rs ref="#pers002">dear boy</rs>, I have some questions. Where does <rs ref="#pers001">he</rs> come from?</l>
<l>Where’s his country, his birth, his father’s old estates?</l>
<l>Did he bring some news of <rs ref="#pers003">your father, his return</rs>?</l>
<l>Or did <rs ref="#pers001">he</rs> come on business of his own?</l>
<l>How he leapt to his feet and off he went!</l>
<l>No waiting around for proper introductions.</l>
<l>And no mean man, not by the looks of him, I’d say.”</l>
<l>“<persName ref="#pers032">Eurymachus</persName>,” <persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName> answered shrewdly,</l>
<l>“clearly <rs ref="#pers003">my father</rs>’s journey home is lost forever.</l>
<l>I no longer trust in rumors—rumors from the blue—</l>
<l>nor bother with any prophecy, when <rs ref="#pers007">mother</rs> calls</l>
<l>some wizard into the house to ask him questions.</l>
<l>As for <rs ref="#pers001">the stranger</rs> though,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers001">the man’s</rs> <rs  ref="#pers001">an old family friend</rs>, from <placeName ref="#place017">Taphos</placeName>,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers021"><rs ref="#pers023">wise <persName ref="#pers023">Anchialus</persName>’</rs> son</rs>. He says his name is <persName ref="#pers021">Mentes</persName>,</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers021">lord of the <orgName ref="#org001">Taphian men</orgName></rs> <rs>who love their oars.”</rs></l>
<l>So <rs ref="#pers002">he</rs> said but deep in his mind he knew <rs ref="#pers001">the immortal goddess</rs>.</l>
<l>Now <orgName ref="#org002">the suitors</orgName> turned to dance and song,</l>
<l>to the lovely beat and sway,</l>
<l>waiting for dusk to come upon them there ...</l>
<l>and the dark night came upon them, lost in pleasure.</l>
<l>Finally, to bed. Each to his own house.</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers002">Telemachus</persName>, off to his bedroom built in the fine courtyard—</l>
<l>a commanding, lofty room set well apart—</l>
<l>retired too, his spirit swarming with misgivings.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers034">His devoted nurse</rs> attended him, bearing a glowing torch,</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers034">Eurycleia</persName> <rs ref="#pers034">the daughter of <persName ref="#pers035">Ops</persName></rs>, <rs ref="#pers035"><persName ref="#pers036">Pisenor</persName>’s son</rs>.</l>
<l><persName ref="#pers024">Laertes</persName> had paid a price for <rs ref="#pers034">the woman</rs> years ago,</l>
<l>still in the bloom of youth. <rs ref="#pers024">He</rs> traded twenty oxen,</l>
<l>honored <rs ref="#pers034">her</rs> on a par with <rs ref="#pers037">his own loyal wife</rs> at home</l>
<l>but fearing <rs ref="#pers037">the queen</rs>’s anger, never shared <rs ref="#pers034">her</rs> bed.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers034">She</rs> was <rs ref="#pers002"><rs ref="#pers024">his</rs>grandson</rs>’s escort now and bore a torch,</l>
<l>for <rs ref="#pers002">she</rs> was the one of all the maids who loved</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers002">the prince</rs> the most—<rs ref="#pers034">she</rs>’d nursed him as a baby.</l>
<l><rs ref="#pers002">He</rs> spread the doors of his snug, well-made room,</l>
<l>sat down on the bed and pulled his soft shirt off,</l>
<l>tossed it into the <rs ref="#pers034">old woman</rs>’s conscientious hands,</l>
<l>and after folding it neatly, patting it smooth,</l>
<l>she hung it up on a peg beside his corded bed,</l>
<l>then padded from the bedroom,</l>
<l>drawing the door shut with the silver hook,</l>
<l>sliding the doorbolt home with its rawhide strap.</l>
<l>There all night long, wrapped in a sheep’s warm fleece,</l>
<l>he weighed in his mind the course <persName type="deity" ref="#pers001">Athena</persName> charted.</l>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
